Guide to the Papers of Simon Dubnow (1860-1941) 1589-1938, 1961 (bulk 1700-1900) RG 87
Center for Jewish History, Publisher.
- Series V: Miscellaneous, 1760-1921; 15 folders
  - Lists[V.4], undated (Folder 980, Item 75183-75206)
    d) listing of 48 Jewish and Christian prisoners arrested in connection with the Velizh trial, Russian
  - Lists[V.4], 1817 (Folder 980, Item 75183-75206)
    e) letter from the Minister of Education, Count Golitsin, to the Governor of Grodno, dated 6 March, about the annulment of the Velizh blood libel, Russian copy
  - Regulating Jewish emigration[V.5], 1890 (Folder 981, Item 75207-75214)
    letter, Russian, copy with addenda
    letter to the Jewish intelligentsia, Russian, 8 pp.
  - Proposal for establishing Jewish caucuses in European parliaments[V.6], 1906 (Folder 981, Item 75214-75239)
    by Simon Bernfeld, copy, German, 25 pp.
  - Minutes of the committee to publish documents about the blood libel trials in Russia[V.7], 1920 (Folder 982, Item 75240-75371)
    meetings during 1919 and 1920, Russian, 133 pp.
    missing minutes of the first meeting, one sheet from the second, as well as minutes from the last two sessions
  - Velizh trial[V.8], 1816, 1828 (Folder 983, Item 75372-75438)
    Grodno, Russian, copies, 65 pp.
  - Vilna Archeographic Commission, Northwest, and Southwest[V.9], 1902 (Folder 984, Item 75439-75493)
    table of contents of Jewish-related documents, 93 pp., text and prefatory page, Russian, assembled by Dubnow
    supplements: two notes by Dubnow regarding documents in the Vilna Archives
    a letter from Gurshovsky of Vilna, about the Jewish statutes, Russian, 2 pp., 26 February
  - Excerpts from a book by Kostamarov[V.10], 1870 (Folder 985, Item 75494-75505)
    prepared by Dubnow, Russian, 8 pp.
    Reel 77
  - Listings from various Russian periodicals[V.11], 1891-1892 (Folder 985, Item 75506-75517)
    list made in Rostov-Don
    Istoricheskii Vestnik, 1882-1890
    Russkii Arkhiv, 1864-1873
  - Listings from various Russian periodicals[V.11], undated (Folder 985, Item 75506-75517)
    list is undated
    Kievskaya Starina, 1882
  - Nayeste Veltkunde (periodical)[V.12], 1798 (Folder 985, Item 75518-75519)
    volume I, #1, January, 4 pp. German
  - (Missing) Project to establish the Alliance Israelite[V.13], 1858-1860 (Folder 985)
    French, 9 pp.
  - Program for the Jewish-Democratic Party[V.14], 1905 (Folder 985, Item 75520-75522)
    founded by Bramson et al, St. Petersburg, February, copy, Russian, 3 pp. folio, with remarks by Dubnow in Russian
  - Nahum Sokolow’s letters[V.15], 1906 (Folder 985, Item 75523A–75523H)
    dealing with his work on the history of Jewish emancipation in Western Europe and Jewish representations in parliaments
    letters to: Y.L. Goldberg, Dubnow, and others in Vilna and to Heinrich Rosenbaum in Bucharest, Hebrew
  - Jewish Education in St. Petersburg[V.16], undated (Folder 986, Item 75524-75532)
    a) proposal for establishing a Jewish religious institute in St. Petersburg, 4 pp., typed, Russian
  - Jewish Education in St. Petersburg[V.16], 1911 (Folder 986, Item 75524-75532)
    b) minutes of the three meetings of the Pedagogic Council of the Baron Guenzburg Higher Courses in Oriental Studies, St. Petersburg, 3 pp., Russian
  - Jewish Education in St. Petersburg[V.16], 1902 (Folder 986, Item 75524-75532)
    c) program of the Baron Guenzburg Higher Courses in Oriental Studies, 2 pp., Russian
  - Role of the government in the deporting of Jews in the World War, 1914-1915[V.17], undated (Folder 986, Item 75533-75543)
    report, Russian typescript, 22 pp.
  - Jewish expropriators in Yekaterinoslav[V.18], undated (Folder 986, Item 75544-75550)
    a) report of executions of Jews in Yekaterinoslav jails, Russian, typescript, 2 pp.
  - Jewish expropriators in Yekaterinoslav[V.18], 1908 (Folder 986, Item 75544-75550)
    b) letter from the Yekaterinoslav Police Chief to the rabbi, 20 November
  - Jewish expropriators in Yekaterinoslav[V.18], 1906 (Folder 986, Item 75544-75550)
    c) letter to the rabbi regarding burial of expropriators, Russian, 4 pp.
    the matter occurred in May, the letter is dated 16 December
  - Jewish expropriators in Yekaterinoslav[V.18], undated (Folder 986, Item 75544-75550)
    d) copies of letters by B.Y. Toporovsky, who sent the above documents to Dubnow
  - World War I in 1914-1915[V.19] (Folder 986, Item 75551-75558)
    a) report by Georg Brandes on the situation in the war zone on the eastern front, Politicken, 26 October, No. 299, Russian, typescript, 6 pp.
  - World War I in 1914-1915[V.19] (Folder 986, Item 75551-75558)
    b) description of the grave situation by a 13 year-old girl, Russian translation, typescript, 2 pp.
  - The disturbances of 1918[V.20] (Folder 987, Item 75559-75563)
    a) atrocities by Polish legionnaires in the towns, Russian, 3 pp.
  - The disturbances of 1918[V.20] (Folder 987, Item 75559-75563)
    b) report by Y. Kopelovitsh about the polish legionnaires in Starye Dorogi, Russian, 2 pp.
  - Archives of the Justice Ministry[V.21], 1798-1800 (Folder 987, Item 75564-75585)
    excerpts from various documents, prepared by the Archeographic Commission (continuation from V.9) assembled by Dubnow, Russian
    primarily about the Vilna kehilla and its trial, 1799-1800
    also about the Jewish delegation to St. Petersburg in 1798
  - Book by Dr. M. Friedlander[V.22], 1883 (Folder 987, Item 75586-75587)
    Zur geschichte der Blutbeschuldigungen gegen di Juden in Mitlalter un in der Neuzeit … nach die Quellen darzustellen, 1871-1883 (about blood libel since the medieval period), 3rd edition, Vienna, 2 pp., German
  - Permission for Rahel Segal to remain in the city in order to prepare for baptism[V.23], 1893 (Folder 988, Item 75588)
    photocopy, remarks by Dubnow, St. Petersburg, 14 February
  - Approvals for the shas (set of Talmud)[V.24], 1904 (Folder 988, Item 75589-75590)
    torn out of a volume of Gemara, printed at the end of the 18th century in Nowy Dwor
    approbation letter from the Vilna beit din, 6 Adar, 5463 (1743), Hebrew, 1 pp., in a letter sent to Vilna from Ryazan, 8 June
  - (Missing) Ketubah for Avraham Hayim, son of Pinhas and Avigayl, daughter of Mula Aliz Badal[V.25], 1862 (Folder 988)
    Bukhara, 10 Adar, 5522, 1pp., Hebrew square lettering
  - (Missing) Letter to the Community in Miedzybozh from Teveriah(Tiberias) [V.26], 1821 (Folder 988)
    about support for the Sefardim and the grave of R’ Meyer Ba'al ha-Ness, 5481, Hebrew and Aramaic, 1 pp.
  - Text for an oath in Yiddish[V.27], 1844 (Folder 988, Item 75591)
    printed in Russian transcription, with various signatures, dated 14 July, 1 pp.
  - Solicitation to collect folksongs[V.28], 1898 (Folder 988, Item 75592)
    by S. Ginzburg and P. Marek, April, Russian, 1 pp.
  - Istoricheskii Vestnik[V.29], 1870-1887 (Folder 988, Item 75593-75611)
    clippings about Jews, notebook, 15 pp. and 2 pieces numbered 16 and 17
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], 1760 (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    a) text of a gravestone, dated Thursday, 17 Iyar 5407
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], undated (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    b) text of memorial to the martyrs (victims) of Zaslav
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], 1892 (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    c) Kedoshei Zaslav by Yosef Kantortshik, issues #195 and #198
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], 1893 (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    d) R’ Matityahu Delakrut, by Aharon Kaminka, issue #234, 23 October
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], 1894 (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    e) salhonim (supplications, prayers), eloquent texts from the pinkas of the bikur holim, dated 5524 (1764)
    note from Lvov, about the victims Hayim and Yehoshua Reytsis, Hamelitz #143, dated 23 June
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], 1894 (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    f) chronicles of Jews from the Horodno area for the year 5524 (1764) by Sh. Viner, Hamelitz #148
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], 1894 (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    g) Memorial Day, by Hillel Shteynshnayder
  - Clippings from Hamelitz[V.30], 1894 (Folder 989, Item 75612-75621)
    h) listings of the Jewish events in Volhynia, by Yehiel Zatulovsky
  - Yiddish and Hebrew clippings from various publications[V.31], 1906 (Folder 990, Item 75622-75627)
    a) from Der Veg (The Road), 21 June, about economic terror
  - Yiddish and Hebrew clippings from various publications[V.31], 1906 (Folder 990, Item 75622-75627)
    b) from Der Veg, 28 July, a letter from Laufman, about anarchism
  - Yiddish and Hebrew clippings from various publications[V.31], 1906 (Folder 990, Item 75622-75627)
    c) from Fraynd (Friend), about Murafa, in Podolia Province
  - Yiddish and Hebrew clippings from various publications[V.31], 1906 (Folder 990, Item 75622-75627)
    d) from Hazman, call from a former member of the Duma of Wyborg, 14 July
  - Yiddish and Hebrew clippings from various publications[V.31], 1906 (Folder 990, Item 75622-75627)
    e) from Hazman, 10 June, about Bialystok pogrom
  - Yiddish and Hebrew clippings from various publications[V.31], undated (Folder 990, Item 75622-75627)
    f) from Fraynd, about the martyrs of Pavoloch
  - Russian clippings from various publications[V.32], 1890-1921 (Folder 990, Item 75628-75633)
    eight clippings about the pogrom in Niezhin vicinity, and other topics
  - Clippings from Voskhod[V.33], 1903 (Folder 991, Item 75634-75635)
    documents about Jews in Chernigov and Brest Litovsk, from issues #51 and 52, documents dating from 1648 and 1654
  - Review of Yevreyskaya Starina[V.34], 1919 (Folder 991, Item 75636-75637)
    from volume X, off-print, in Russian, 2 pp.
- Series VI: Literaria, 1662-1938; 26 folders
  This series contains biographical materials about notable rabbinical figures, mainly from the territory of Poland.
  - Letters from R’ Yosef Levinshteyn[VI.1], 1894-1895, undated (Folder 992, Item 75638-75656)
    about various rabbis in Poland, starting with RaShal (R’ Shloyme Luria) and ReMa (R’ Moshe Isserlis), and also about the earliest Hasidic leaders (R’ David of Makow, the Tishevitser “Moshiakh”), the martyrs of Lublin from 1636, and R' Nahman Adler, Serock, 11 letters, Hebrew
  - Introduction to the book Vikuah mayim hayim[VI.2], 1712 (Folder 993, Item 75657-75664)
    by R’ Khayim son of Betsalel, Amsterdam, 5472, copy, 8 pp., Hebrew
  - Letter from Ya’akov Shapiro[VI.3], 1895 (Folder 993, Item 75665-75669)
    about the situation of the rabbis and the state of Hebrew language in 17th century Poland, 10 Elul 5655, Mezrich, 5 pp., with copies of various religious books, Hebrew
  - Introduction and approvals to the book Ir-David (City of David)[VI.4], undated (Folder 993, Item 75670-75677)
    by R’ David Lida from the year 1680-1681, about the pogrom in Lvov of 5424 (1664) and the names of the rabbis of that time
    written by Meyer Itkin of Kastsyukovitski, Mohilev Gubernia, in a Hebrew letter to Dubnow, 8 pp.
  - Excerpts from the book Panim me'irot – responsa[VI.5], 1715 (Folder 994, Item 75678-75679)
    by R’ Meyer son of Yitshak of Szydlowce, Amsterdam, 5475, two volumes, and other notes, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Genealogy records of the Margolius family[VI.6], 1808 (Folder 994, Item 75680-75681)
    from manuscript by R’ Tzvi-Hirsh Margolius, dated 5568, sent to Dubnow by Dr. Chazanovitsh with a notation by Yosef Melnik, the copyist, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Approval by the Rabbi of Maciejow, R’ Shmuel son of Hayim Lanzer[VI.7], 1790 (Folder 994, Item 75682)
    approval for Sefer Harefues by Dr. Moyshe Markusi, Poryck, 5550, Hebrew, 1 pp.
  - Public notice about the misuse of the quotations and writings of the Gaon of Vilna[VI.8], 1800 (Folder 994, Item 75683-75684)
    from the Vilna Calendar for the year 5560, sent to Dubnow by Dr. Chazanovitsh, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Introduction by Louis Meyer to his autobiography[VI.9], 1871 (Folder 994, Item 75685-75688)
    copied from his book, Berlin, German and Hebrew, 4 pp.
  - Letter from Feivel Frenkl[VI.10], 1893 (Folder 994, Item 75689-75690)
    about R’ Shlomo and his son R’ Yehudah of Lublin and the elegy about their deaths, from the book Shalshelet ha-kabbalah, Kiev, 24 Tamuz 5653, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Statutes of the Three Kehillot/Communities[VI.11], 1715 (Folder 994, Item 75691-75694)
    copy of the book, Altona, Hamburg and Wandsbeck, dated 5475, clothing laws, from the copy in the Strashun Library in Vilna
    with comments by Shteynshnayder on Kirya ne’emanah (The Faith of the City), copied by Gershovski, Vilna, 7 pp., Hebrew, with Yiddish mixed in
  - Letters and a homily by R’ Azriel Leib Rakovski[VI.12], 1880 (Folder 995, Item 75695-75696)
    chief of the beit din of Plock in the year 5640, concerning his rabbinate in Mstislavl, with a remark by Dubnow’s brother, Ze’ev-Volf, Hebrew, 2 pp.
  - Appeal of acquittal for the brothers Yehezkel and David[VI.13], 1831 (Folder 995, Item 75697)
    sons of R’ Avraham Yehudah-Leib Segal (aka Laybl Vilkiyer) and a request for their support, in the time of their trials in court, issued by the beit din and kehilla of Vilna, with signatures and a seal, 21 Kislev, 5592, original, 1 pp.
  - Invocation in honor of the crowning of the Tsar Nicholas in 1894[VI.14], 1896 (Folder 995, Item 75698-75710)
    by Menahem Nahum Litinsky, dated 5656, in the form of a drama, Hebrew, 12 pp.
    supplemented by a letter in Hebrew from Litinsky, dated 10 Tamuz 5656, about printing this song as a present to the Emperor, with a remark by Dubnow: “I advised the writer not to commit such a folly,” 1 pp.
  - Todah ha-ba'ah le-aharei ha-zeman (Thanks that came too late)[VI.15], 1878 (Folder 995, Item 75711-75714)
    by Yehudah Leib Gordon, composed in 5638, not printed for reasons of censorship
    copy by Ya’akov Bohuslavsky of Nikolayev, Hebrew, 3 pp.
    supplementary letter from Y. Bohuslavsky about the manuscript and a remark by Dubnow that it is to be printed in the future as a “curiosum” with a short introduction
  - Teater fun Khasidim, undated (Folder 996, Item 75715-75762)
    in 3 separate acts, performed in Lvov, 1839-1843
    printed in Historishe Shriftn
  - Responsa between Lithuanian and Lubavich Rebbes and the rabbis of the surrounding areas, ca.1820-1829 (Folder 997, Item 75763-75815)
    handwritten notebook
  - Sefer beit Aharon, 1843 (Folder 998, Item 75816-75969)
    by Rabbi Aharon of Karlin
    notebook of copies of letters and miscellaneous other documents by Hasidic rabbis
    bears the seal of the YIVO Archives in Vilna, and a note sent by A. Federman of Luck
    YIVO sent it to Dubnow
  - Sihot ha-Ran ve-sippurim me-R’ Nahman mi-Bratslav, 1891 (Folder 999, Item 75970-76034)
    Bratslaver homilies and stories, manuscript, 5586 (1826), with Dubnow’s written comments and annotations
    received from Ya’akov Shapiro from Berdichev, Poland, Nissan, 5651
    numbered “Hasidiana No. 9” and “VII.8”
  - Personal documents of Polish inhabitants of Vilna, 17th-19th centuries, 1863-1872 (Folder 1000, Item 76035-76107)
    includes a last will, and documents related to disposition of real estate property in Vilna, Polish and Latin
    several documents regarding properties in Warsaw and Nowy Dwor belonging to the couple Leib vel Ludwik Feigin and Braindel vel Barbara Muhlrad Feigin
  - Chronicle of the blood libel in Mezrich in the year 5576 (1815-1816), 1892 (Folder 1001, Item 76108-76119)
    Ya’akov Shapiro, 5652
  - Bukharan ketubah, 1662 (Folder 1001, Item 76120)
    dated 5422
  - Receipt for toll duty paid by a Jew, 1849 (Folder 1001, Item 76121)
    Warsaw
  - Letter by Dubnow about the blood libel in Telsiai in 1827, undated (Folder 1001, Item 76122)
  - Documents and correspondence with O. Grunenberg, 1890 (Folder 1002, Item 76123-76140)
    about anti-Jewish statements made by officials in Mstislavl
  - Genesis of a ritual lie, 1882, 1913 (Folder 1003, Item 76141-76146)
    article by Dubnow about blood libels, written in connection with the Beilis trial, printed in Dien, 1913
    a circular by Lutostansky about his book on blood libels, 1882
  - The debate (kultur-kampf) in the Odessa branch of the Hevrei Mefitzei Haskalah, 1901-1902 (Folder 1004, Item 76147-76223)
    about establishing a national Jewish school network in Russia
    includes letters by F. Lander, secretary of the Odessa branch, to Dubnow, about initiating teacher training courses and Dubnow’s suggestion about reforming the program in line with the spirit of the Jewish schools
  - Kishinev Pogrom, April 20, 1903 (Folder 1005, Item 76224-76243)
    correspondence, appeal in Hebrew, by Agudat Soferim Ivri'im (The Union of Hebrew Writers)
    drafts by Dubnow, including a letter for L. Tolstoy’s signature and an article in Voskhod confiscated by the censor
    a letter to M. Dizengoff
  - Projected declaration by Russian Jewry about the patriotic duty of Jews in wartime and about the hopes of achieving equality, 1915 (Folder 1006, Item 76244-76248)
    copies, includes Dubnow’s editorial comments, January
  - Zurich conference about Jewish rights, 1927 (Folder 1007, Item 76249-76290)
    speech by Dubnow, report, dispatches by the Jewish Telegraphic Agency, press reports in Yiddish, German, Russian
    Reel 78
  - Shalom Schwarzbard trial, 1927 (Folder 1008, Item 76291-76299)
    press statements
  - Enquiry from Funk and Wagnall publishers about Jesus, 1899-1901 (Folder 1009, Item 76300-76308)
    correspondence with Dubnow, K. Kohler, Nahum Sokolow and others
  - Manuscript about the town Wilki, undated (Folder 1010, Item 76309-76316)
    by Avraham Yehudah-Leib ben Mordekhai Markus
  - Dubnow’s answers responses to the greetings on his 70th birthday, 1930 (Folder 1011, Item 76317-76332)
    notes, envelopes
  - Sefer Megillas Sedorim Lehisaneg Lifney Heykhal Oyneg, 1884 (Folder 1012, Item 76333-76373)
    Prague, 5551-5552 (1791-1792), by R’ Yehuda, son of Mordekhai ha-Levi, Ish Hurvits, Warsaw
    reprint, with Dubnow’s written comments (a parody, a debate between a Talmudist and a Kabbalist)
  - Books from Dubnow’s library, 1895-1899 (Folder 1013, Item 76374-76567)
    Isaac Hirsch Weiss, Zikhronotai (My Memoirs), Warsaw 5655 (1895)
    Be’er Yitzhak (Isaac’s Well) by David Ber Natansohn, Warsaw, 1899, with Dubnow’s marginalia
    the two books were bought in December 1950 from the bookstore of Veri Fisher who had acquired it from Dr. Louis Levin, Breslau
  - Dubnow’s memoirs, 1932-1933, undated (Folder 1014, Item 76568-76596)
    clippings of chapters published in Folksblat, Der Tog and Di Tsukunft
    Sh. Niger’s articles about the memoirs, 1932-1933
  - World History of the Jewish People, undated (Folder 1015, Item 76597-76760)
    Russian manuscripts of volume III
  - World History of the Jewish People, 1936 (Folder 1016, Item 76761-77032)
    proofs of the German edition of volume I
  - Various articles by Dubnow, 1927-1938 (Folder 1017, Item 77033-77080)
    including articles about:
    a 1927 conference
    national liberation movements
    World Jewish Congress in the years 1935-1938
    Soviet Russia and the Jews, 1928
    Yiddish, Hebrew, Russian
    Reel 79
- Series VII: Letters to Dubnow, 1885-1931, 1961; 26 folders
  This series consists of letters written to Dubnow. A large part of the series consists of letters from zamlers (collectors) from the 1890s who participated in the search for Jewish historical materials. The correspondence is replete with discussions about documents, their location, availability, etc. The other letters in this series are from fellow historians and other scholars, including Yitzhak Antonovski, Martin Buber, Shim’on Goldlast, Elias Tcherikower, Maxim Vinaver, Max Weinreich, and Chaim Zhitlowsky. The number of letters is in parentheses.
  - Dubnow’s ad-hoc notes on the envelopes, undated (Folder 1018, Item 77081-77087)
  - Aleph א, 1894-1896, 1924-1931 (Folder 1019, Item 77088-77102)
    Shmuel Alexandrovich, Bobruisk, (1), 5655 (1895)
    Vitali A. Olkin, Riga, (2), 1894
    Yitzhak Antonovski, Odessa, (1), 5656 (1896)
    Simhah Assaf, Jerusalem, (2), 5684-5685, 5691 (1924-1925 and 1931)
  - Beys ב, 1891-1900, 1931 (Folder 1020, Item 77103-77139)
    Barukh Bobis, (1), 1893
    Martin Buber, (1), 1931
    Ben-Tsion Baranov (1), 1891
    A. B. Bialostotski, Mezrich, (2), 1891
    M. Buber, Ostroh, Volhynia, (4), 1894
    Shmaryahu Beylin, (4), 1893-1897
    Shakhnah-Meyer Bernshteyn, Ozorkow, (2), 1892
    Shloyme-Meyer Bernshteyn, Kedainia, (1)
    Mathias Bersohn, Warsaw, (5), 1895
    A. Bramson, (3), and documents, 1899-1900
  - Gimel ג, 1892-1927 (Folder 1021, Item 77140-77220)
    Eliahu ha-Levi Gabrielev, Nesvizh, 1893
    Shim'on Goldlast, Lomza, (1), 5652 (1892)
    Hirsh-Leib Goldenberg, Bohuslav (2), 5655 (1895)
    Yitzhak-Meyer Granetman, Pinczow, (1)
    Nahum Grinhauz, and Simhah Koptshik
    Trakiai, (1), 5654 (1894) and Dubnow’s answer
    Shakhnah Grinfeld, Barandovka, (2), 5654 (1894)
    Grinfeld hareini ba-sadeh, (2)
    Yuli Gessen, (13)
    Girshovsky, (10), 1895
    L. Gots, Gorodok (3), 1893-1894
    Ila Galant, (6), 1896-1927
  - Gimel-Hey ג-ה, 1892-1931 (Folder 1022, Item 77221-77287)
    Yosef-Hayim Dorozhko, (1)
    A. Druyanov, (1), 1902
    M. Halperin, (1), 1895
    Shmuel Abba Horodetsky, (4), 1895-1931
    Iser Hutin, Rostov-Don (2), 1925
    A. Sh. Hirshberg, (1), 1897
    Girshovsky, (24), 1892-1895
  - Vov ו, 1893-1896, 1931 (Folder 1023, Item 77288-77298)
    Volf Vaynshteyn, Kishinev, (1), 1894
    Yehudah-Leib Vaysman, Lipoviets, gravestone inscriptions, (2), 1893-1896
    Shmuel-Tzvi Veltsman, Kalisz, (3), 5654 (1894)
    M. Vilenski, Berlin, (1), 1931
  - Vov ו, 1921-1925 (Folder 1024, Item 77299-77345)
    Maxim Vinaver, Paris, (3), 1922-1923
    17 letters from Dubnow to Vinaver, 1921-1925
  - Zayin-Khes ז-ח, 1892-1897 (Folder 1025, Item 77346-77364)
    D. Z. Zakharin, Odessa, (1), 1896
    A. Zaks, Lubashovka (1)
    Shmuel Zilbershteyn, Warsaw, (1), 1893, also a copy of a letter from Zilbershteyn to A. E. Landau
    Khayim Ziskind, Berdichev, (1), 1897
    N. Zlatkin, Rostov, (2), 1892
    M. Khazan, Polonaya, (2), 1894
    Shalom ha-Kohen Kharif, Zaslav, (1)
  - Khes-Khaf ח-כ, 1885-1900, 1931 (Folder 1026, Item 77365-77396)
    Avraham Taub, Timisvar, (German) (1), 1931
    V. Turbov, Kronsch (1), 1894
    Pinhas ha-Kohen Turberg, Jedwabne, (5), 1894-1895
    Sholem Yampolsky, (1), 1895
    Hirsh Yofe, Homel, (4), 1892-1896
    B. Chawkin, Lodz, (1), 1892
    Dr. Yosef Chazanovitsh, (10), 1885-1900
  - Lamed-Mem ל-מ, 1888-1898 (Folder 1027, Item 77397-77416)
    A. Leon (1), 1892
    Mordekhai-Nahum Litinsky, Mohilev, Podolski (2), 1892
    Yisrael Levi, St. Petersburg, (3), 1889-1890
    Yitzhak-Meyer Levinshteyn, Kosice, (1), 5654 (1894)
    Aharon Levit, Kishinev, (1)
    Ya'akov Marshak, Warsaw, (1) 1896
    Hayim Volf Margolis, Dubno, (2), 1893-1894
    Mendel Bik, Ostroh, (2), 1888
    Aharon-Moshe Mazurski, Ruzhana, Brody Gubernia, (1), 1898
  - Nun-Ayin נ-ע, 1892-1899, 1928 (Folder 1028, Item 77417-77453)
    Yitzhak Nisenbaum (1), 1895
    Shlomo Nisenbaum, Lublin (1), 1899
    Moshe Nashburg, Avrutch, (1), 1893
    Isser Nastoshkin (1), 1895
    Semyon M. Stanislavsky, Yekaterinoslav, (2), 1894
    B. Segal, Zagare, Kovno Province, (2), 1894
    L. N. Etinger, Velizh, Vitebsk Province, (1), 1892
    Moshe Ehrlich, Lublin, (4), 1928
  - Pey-Fey פ-פֿ, 1891-1898, 1931 (Folder 1029, Item 77454-77490)
    Shmuel Figit, Yekaterinoslav (1)
    D. Pinsker, Odessa, (1), 1893
    V. D. Pevzner (1), 1893
    Pinhas Pesis, Kovel (1), 1892
    Avraham-Leib Faynshteyn, Brest-Litovsk, (1), 1892
    Yosef-Zundel Finkelshteyn (1), 1892
    Hayim Dov-Berish Fridberg, (5), Antwerp, (3), 1931
    L. Fridland, St. Petersburg, (1), 1893
    Yisrael Fridlander, Berlin, (2), 1898
    Bernard A. Fridman, Birzai, (5), 1891-1892
  - Kuf ק, 1888-1898 (Folder 1030, Item 77491-77516)
    Sha'ul Kazarnovsky, Lyadi, (2), 1893